<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Elogy against occasion requires upon the Earl of Shaftsbury calculated for the meridion of eighty one.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19730729</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19730729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1698:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Elogy against occasion requires upon the Earl of Shaftsbury calculated for the meridion of eighty one.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ab. Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109385:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ELOGY, Againſt Occaſion Requires UPON THE Earl of Shaftsbury. Calculated for the Meridion of <hi>Eighty One.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AT the Weſt-End of th' Univerſal Frame,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Place</hi> there lies, which ſome <hi>a Land</hi> miſ-name;</l>
               <l>An Excrement of World, call'd <hi>Natures Sinke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Maſs of undrain'd mire, quag, bogg, and ſtinke.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> Yclep'd, When th' All-creating <hi>WORD</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great Natures Architect, and Orders Lord</l>
               <l>From Nothing ſpoke out All, and all around</l>
               <l>With Form, Light, Beauty, and perfection Grownd;</l>
               <l>This <hi>Spot</hi> alone ner'e heard th' Almighty found</l>
               <l>This heap of Undigeſted Earth! a Place,</l>
               <l>Which of old <hi>Chaos</hi> wears th' Original Face!</l>
               <l>As if the Out-caſt of the Works of Heaven;</l>
               <l>'T had ſcarce <hi>one days</hi> Creation out of <hi>Seven.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Country's by a ſort of Natives Man'd,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Braines,</hi> as much unfurniſh'd as their <hi>Land;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But yet, what e're they want in <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is made up in their <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH</hi> and <hi>INNOCENCE</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such Innocence born in ſo pure an Air,</l>
               <l>Their very Ground will nought that's Poyſonous bear</l>
               <l>Since it was waſht with the laſt <hi>Maſſacre.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> ROME's Memorable toyle,</l>
               <l>Which like the Plague, ſtop't by ore-flowing <hi>Nile</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Purg'd all Envenom'd Locuſts from their ſoyle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With a full Pack of this untainted Brood,</l>
               <l>Is Hunted <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> to Death purſu'd.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109385:2"/>
               <l>All nobly ſworn to hang the <hi>Heretick Dogg,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An <hi>Oath's</hi> no more, then their own Natural <hi>Bogg,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ore which, the nimble <hi>Torie</hi> ſafely runs</l>
               <l>Whilſt the more flow pac'd daſtard <hi>ſtick's and drown's.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yes, <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> for his <hi>Damnation</hi> call,</l>
               <l>For he knows <hi>Rome,</hi> and he deſerv's to Fall!</l>
               <l>Thy Greatneſs, <hi>Rome,</hi> by Myſtick ſteps Aſcends,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Blind</hi> and <hi>Ignorant</hi> are thy <hi>beſt Friends:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reaſon and truth to <hi>Thee</hi> are Foes and Spies,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Great Infallability,</hi> be wiſe,</l>
               <l>And ſafely <hi>Cut off Heads,</hi> to <hi>put out Eyes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Favours in Pallaces, let no man boaſt,</l>
               <l>Where but to <hi>See,</hi> and <hi>Know,</hi> is to be <hi>Loſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So in the Great <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Court of old,</l>
               <l>Such Honour did the darling <hi>Ovid</hi> hold,</l>
               <l>Long on his Brows the Royal Laurels hung,</l>
               <l>Whilſt he ſoft Airs, to flattered <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſung,</l>
               <l>Till by a <hi>prying Eye</hi> undone, he's ſent</l>
               <l>Damn'd for a <hi>look,</hi> t' Eternal Baniſhment:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yes, in thy Chains, Great <hi>Overbury</hi> lye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> is not <hi>Rome,</hi> till <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Dangers</hi> dye:</l>
               <l>To Preſerve <hi>Nations, Right, Religion, Kings,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are for Unhallowed hands, two Sacred things.</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Cauſe 'tis Fatal to embark,</l>
               <l>Like the bold <hi>Jew</hi> that <hi>propt</hi> the <hi>falling Ark,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With an unlicenc'd Arm he durſt approach,</l>
               <l>And tho' to <hi>Save,</hi> yet it was <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>touch.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Go blaſted then, and branded to thy Doom,</l>
               <l>With no leſs Stains, then <hi>hateing Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Supplanting France,</hi> and <hi>Saveing Chriſtendom.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ab. Green,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
